PROFESSOR: So what about
utilities in humans?
We say there is a utility function that
can capture all of your rich and
nuanced preferences.
What is that utility function?
How would I get it?
How would I figure out that the value
you associate with Thai food is 3.7?
First, we need a utility scale.
Often people work with what are called
normalized utilities, where the best
you can get is 1 and the worst
you can get a zero.
But there's a lot of scales people use
that are adjusted for both reasoning
about certain scenarios and also for
elicitation in those scenarios.
So for example, a lot of these utility
scales are actually kind of morbid,
because a lot of the times, by the
time you're dredging up numerical
computations of utilities with humans,
you're actually talking about very,
very difficult decisions that are hard
because there are very serious
consequences.
So for example, there's the micromort.
The micromort is a one-millionth
chance of death.
I told you this would be morbid.
Why is this useful?
This is useful because you have to
reason about things like, should we
recall a product?
And you want to think about, what are
the risks and what are the rewards in
each scenario and what are
the probabilities?
You need to put these
things on a scale.
And when you're talking about things
like product safety, often you really
are talking about chance of death.
And so that's your utility scale.
It's not the only one.
A lot of the others are also
morbid but important.
So for example, medical reasoning
is often done in
quality-adjusted life years.
Unlike a product risk where the danger
is somebody is going to die and you're
looking aggregate safety, now you're
looking at an individual person and
trying to think about balancing the
fact both that a medical procedure
might change the duration of your
life and also the quality.
And so you try to put your utility
function in a setting where this is
captured in as transparent
a way as possible.
The reason why we can have these
different scales is that behavior is
going to be invariant under any positive
linear transformation.
Of course, if you invert the
sine of the utilities, the
behavior is going to change.
And we saw earlier that if you square
them, the behavior will change.
But positive linear transformations
are safe.
If all you had when you tried to figure
out people's utilities was
prize choices, if I just went to you
and say, do you like chocolate or
strawberry, then I can get a certain
degree down the road.
I could figure out enough, for
example, to do minimax.
But if I actually want to figure out
your rich and nuanced preferences, I
need to ask you questions
about lotteries.
So how do we actually figure out what
these numbers are that encode a
human's utility?
It's really, really hard.
So the standard approach
to assessing utility--
it's often called eliciting
utilities--
looks something like this.
You take your human and you ask them
questions about various things.
And they get to describe
their preferences.
Remember, that's fundamental.
You elicit preferences and then you can
figure out what the utilities are
that encode those preferences.
So what you do is you compare some prize
whose utility you care about to
a standard lottery which is between
something really good and something
really bad.
And you slide the probability until
the human becomes indifferent.
Wherever that probability lands gives
you a way of figuring out what the
utility is.
For example, paying $30.
Do you want to pay $30?
Probably not.
OK.
So what exactly is the utility
we should associate with
this mildly bad thing?
Well, what I do is I
pull out a lottery.
So I say, all right, let's figure out
just exactly how much you don't want
to pay $30.
Well, you're going to have a
lottery between no change--
we're just kidding, you don't
have to pay the $30.
That's better than paying $30.
On the other hand, you
have instant death.
That's worse than paying $30.
And so what we do is we fiddle
with the probabilities.
And once we find that magic probability
that tells you that you're
indifferent, well, now we have some
sense of how bad this $30 payment is.
You know, for most people it's small.
It's a micromort.
If pay $30 was really bad, it was pay $3
million, be in debt for the rest of
your life, you'd probably get
slightly different numbers.
And that reflects the fact that the
utilities of things are going to
depend not just on the prizes in the
lottery, but the probabilities with
which you mix them.
How about money?
As soon as we talk about utilities,
people think, OK, well, let's encode
everything in dollars.
Money, it turns out, does not behave
as a utility function.
But of course, we can talk about
the utility of having money.
In fact, we just did.
So how do we think about money
in the context of utility?
Money certainly has utility.
But it's not a good utility scale.
Why not?
How do we think about these things?
Let's imagine a lottery.
This lottery, you're either going
to get X dollars or Y dollars.
And you get X dollars with probability
p, and Y dollars with the remaining
probability.
So this is some lottery.
Obviously, how good this thing
is depends on X, Y, and p.
Its expected monetary value is simply
the average of the dollar amounts.
I haven't said anything
about utilities here.
I'm just saying there are two dollar
amounts, a probability, and I can
compute the average monetary
value here.
This lottery also has a utility.
And we know, because of how utility
functions work, its utility isn't the
average of the utility of X dollars
and the utility of Y dollars.
It is typically the case, though not
always, that the utility of a lottery
over money is worth less
than the utility of its
expected monetary value.
In this sense, people are basically
risk-averse when it comes to money.
That's what this means.
You'd rather have the smaller value of a
sure thing than the lottery that has
a higher expected monetary value.
And when people are in debt,
they tend to be risk-prone.
Why?
You might think, OK, well, wait.
But some people are more risk-averse
than others.
That's certainly true.
But let's think about it.
What does this graph look like?
You've got money here.
So this is the amount of dollars.
And you've got utility here.
So this is the amount of utility.
Let's say this is zero dollars.
Well, how many of you would
like a million dollars?
A million dollars is good.
It's a little weird that you didn't
all raise your hands.
But a million dollars is pretty good.
It would make a pretty big change in
the quality of most people's lives,
big gain in utility.
Would you like a billion dollars?
Yes.
You would like that more than
a million dollars, please.
Let's say I gave you
a billion dollars.
Now how much do you want
a million dollars?
Oh, whatever.
A million dollars on top of a
billion is not so important.
And that means there's
diminishing returns.
So in terms of your utility, it
looks something like this.
At the beginning, wherever you
are, adding money is good.
Presumably more money stays better
for a typical person.
But it has to level off.
I'm told that after your first trillion
dollars, the second trillion
is of limited utility.
Now what happens when it's negative?
Well, it's kind of got to look
the same in the limit.
Things can only get so bad.
Once you're a billion dollars in debt,
you know, whatever, right?
I mean, presumably at some point
you're too big to fail.
Anyway--
But like it's not exactly symmetric.
It tends to stay this way
and then slowly change.
But it's going to eventually
have to level off.
So let me replace that with an actual
graph from actual data elicited from
actual people.
It looks something like this.
It does level off positive.
It eventually turns risk-prone negative,
but not immediately.
It's not completely symmetric, because
zero isn't particularly
well-defined here.
This is the general behavior of
money and utility interacting.
Because of these kinds of effects with
money, there's a whole industry of
things like insurance.
So let's think about a specific
money lottery.
Let's say you have a lottery of having
a 50/50 chance of either $1,000 or
zero dollars.
This could be, for example, you have
a $1,000 computer and there's a 50%
chance it's going to get stolen, which
would leave you with zero computer.
So you have this lottery.
So lucky you.
What's the expected monetary
value of this lottery.
It's $500.
You just average the dollar amounts.
This lottery that you are currently
holding, your easily-stolen computer,
has expected monetary value of $500.
What is its certainty equivalent?
What's a certainty equivalent?
That is the amount of money that
would be acceptable to you in
place of this lottery.
How much money would you trade this
mixture of $1,000 and zero for?
Who would trade this lottery for $10?
No one.
Who would trade this lottery for $900?
Everyone.
All right.
Who would trade this lottery for $400?
OK.
Most people.
Well, in fact, for most people $400 is
about the certainty equivalent for
this lottery.
It's lower than the expected
monetary value.
But it's not ridiculously lower.
The difference here, that $100 between
the certainty equivalent that you
would accept in place of the lottery and
the actual average monetary value
of this lottery, that's called
the insurance premium.
And the reason there's an insurance
industry is because people are willing
to pay to reduce their risk.
If everyone were completely risk-neutral
in this sense, we
wouldn't need any insurance.
Now maybe this is one of these things
where it's just a scam.
You really shouldn't sign up for
insurance, because really it's just
exploiting your human imperfection.
Not true.
It's win-win.
The reason why this insurance can be
win-win, at least if the numbers work
out the right way, is because you would
actually rather have the $400
than this lottery.
So in doing this trade, you win.
You're happy.
The insurance company would rather
have the lottery than the $400.
Why?
Well, their utility curve is much
flatter, because they're zoomed in.
$10 is nothing to them.
They're zoomed in.
When you zoom in on anything,
it gets pretty flat.
It gets pretty linear.
Also, remember that the insurance
company has a lot of lotteries.
So essentially they benefit from
the central limit theorem.
You don't.
So everybody wins.
You win.
They win.
It's all happy, if the numbers work out
to reflect everybody's utilities.
That's not to say that humans
are perfectly rational.
There are a lot of cases where people
have tried to show that people are
rational where people
are not rational.
And they try to do it with actual
experiments asking people about
questions about their preferences.
So let's do this experiment.
It's a classic experiment.
Here are two lotteries.
Lottery A, you have an 80% chance
of $4,000 or nothing.
And Lottery B, you have a 100%
chance of $3,000 and zero
percent chance of nothing.
Who prefers Lottery A?
Who prefers Lottery B?
OK.
Overwhelming preference for Lottery B.
So Lottery B, overwhelming preference.
Well, that doesn't seem unreasonable.
Let's give you some more lotteries.
Here's C versus D. In C, you have
a 20% chance of $4,000.
And in D, you have a 25%
chance of $3,000.
Who prefers Lottery C?
Lots of people.
Who prefers Lottery D?
A couple people.
We're going to call C the winner.
It turns out that's pretty typical.
Most people like B than A. And most
people like C better than D. What's
the problem?
Well, I can't tell you what the utility
of a certain dollar amount is.
But I could assume that zero is zero.
That's just shifting the scale.
And then assuming that more money is
better here, if B is greater than A,
that means that the utility for
$3k is greater than 0.8 times
the utility for $4k.
And that's fine.
Except if C is better than D, I can look
at those same numbers and just
multiply C and D by four and get
the opposite conclusion.
0.8 times the utility of $4k, whatever
it is, has to be greater than the
utility of $3k.
So what the heck?
You're in a class that I said could be
entitled "Computational Rationality"
and here you are, irrational
preferences.
Are you irrational?
Or did I do something wrong?
Of course you think I
did something wrong.
What did I do wrong, because of
course you're rational, right?
What's going on is there's some subtlety
in how this is phrased.
There's actually a lot going on here.
You could have a very long and very
detailed conversation about how human
utilities actually work.
One important thing that's happening
here is in A, here, I didn't tell you
about the zero.
But the zero is actually
very different.
Here, the zero doesn't really matter.
Here, you have a 20% chance of getting
zero and you receive something else if
you end up with zero under Lottery
A. What do you receive?
You receive the feeling of stupidity.
Nobody likes to feel stupid.
And that's part of one explanation of
why you can look at these outcomes and
say that the model is oversimplified.